Finding Aid for John H. Romani papers, 1957-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John H. Romani papers 1957-1991 1970-1990
Romani, John Henry, 1925-
2 linear feet
991 Aa 2
Professor and administrator in the University of Michigan School of Public Health; files pertaining to Romani's presidency of the American Public Health Association, 1979-1980; correspondence, 1970-1991, mainly professional and relating to the field of public health; and lectures and speeches concerning the public health profession.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by John H. Romani (donor no. 7998 ) in 1991.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
John H. Romani was born in Milan, Italy in 1925. He received his Ph.D. in political science from the University of Michigan in 1955. He served as a professor and administrator in the School of Public Health at the University of Michigan from 1961 until 1969, when he took a position as vice-chancellor of the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. In 1971 he returned to the School of Public Health at Michigan, where he remained until his retirement in 1993. He also served as the president of the American Public Health Association in 1979-1980. In his inaugural address, Romani focused on the budget difficulties of health care organizations and addressed the impact of the environment on public health. During his career, Romani lectured and wrote on public health issues, and served as a mentor to many aspiring public health professionals.
The John Romani Papers consist primarily of correspondence, manuscripts, newspaper clippings and press releases. The collection is organized into three series: American Public Health Association Presidency, Correspondence, and Lectures and Speeches.
Subjects:
Romani, John Henry, 1925-; American Public Health Association.; Public health.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.
- American Public Health Association Presidency
  The American Public Health Association Presidency series documents Romani's election and tenure in the presidency.
  - Correspondence, Clippings, and Press Releases, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Presidential Address, 1979 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series consists of professional correspondence, mostly concerning the field of public health.
  - Chronological
    - 1980 (Box 1)
    - 1981 (Box 1)
    - 1982-1987, 13 folders (Box 1)
  - Alphabetical
    - D-W, 1970-1974, 9 folders (Box 1)
    - A-C, 1980-1981, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - D-Z, 1980-1981, 23 folders (Box 2)
    - A-Z, 1982-1991, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Individuals
    - Robert Brown, 1970-1974 (Box 2)
    - William Haber, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - William L. Hayes, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Bernard James, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - Organizations
    - American Society for Public Administration; Section on Human Resource Administration, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Association of State and Territorial Public Laboratory Directors, 1984 (Box 2)
- Lectures and Speeches
  The Lectures and Speeches series consists of drafts for speaking engagements and several publication manuscripts. Most of the drafts concern the public health profession.
  - Lectures and Speeches, 1957-1980, 4 folders (Box 2)